[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
welcome to stoa everyone i am peter
limberg the steward of the stoa and the
stow is a place for us to cohere and
dialogue about what matters most at the
nice edge of this very moment
and for the new faces here i don't know
how to describe the stoa
it's a digital campfire communal podcast
we have a wisdom gym
that can throw a bunch of other jazzy
terms at you but it's essentially a
place where we have
philosophical or philosophical adjacent
events via zoom
and today we are very lucky because we
have
michael ashcroft joining us today um
how to introduce michael the guy is a
modern or meta-modern if
they're using another jazzy term meta
modern renaissance man
and one of the things in his talent
stack is he is a certified
trainer in the alexander technique
and i will let michael explain what that
is if you have no idea what that is
but how today's going to work is
michael's going to talk about the
alexander technique
and maybe we'll have some exercises in
the
that portion as well so i'll be 30
minutes and then the other 30 minutes is
going to be a q and a
and how those work is you throw your
question in the chat i will unmute you
you call up then you ask your question
michael if you don't want to be on
youtube because this will be on youtube
just indicate that and i'll read it on
your behalf
so that being said michael my friend
good morning
good afternoon how's it going yes good
afternoon i should be time sensitive
um so yeah i'll hand it over to you and
then feel free to
launch the discussion thank you very
much and
thank you to the 48 people who've given
up an hour of your weekend to listen to
me talk about alexander technique
it's a real privilege to be here and i'm
looking forward to sharing
some glimpse of what this thing is all
about
that you can take away and i very much
intend for this to be
in line with the stoic philosophy of
being a virtual campfire
i'm not here to pontificate that to you
i'm not here to
stand on any airs or be formal very much
an informal intimate atmosphere i'd like
to cultivate here so
please come into it with that intention
in mind
um i also want to kind of highlight
something going on and then here in the
uk
i'm in london we are now gearing up for
what looks like six more months of
covered related lockdown measures um
which is
challenging and i think many of us are
in a similar place um
around the world and i'd like to offer
what i have to offer in the spirit of
maybe it being useful in your context if
there's no chance of physical
spaciousness then perhaps there is more
chance of internal spaciousness that you
can access
so the way this will run is it's meant
to be experiential
i have a lot of things i could say at
you
i'm holding back on doing that and
instead i'm going to take one pathway
through this
with the idea being that you get a
glimpse of there being something here
that there's a there there that you can
access
and before i go into some of these these
topics
i'd like to invite you first of all to
notice a couple of things just check in
with yourself and first of all notice
how much effort are you putting in right
now globally
just to be to understand what i'm saying
to to figure out what's coming next
there's often a sense of some kind of
lingering
doing that's going on and if you just
assign a number to it between one and
ten like where roughly these your your
carrying dial your effort dial
right now and oh two and
out of ten in the chat that's fantastic
you don't need my help um for everyone
else
um one more thing i'd like to ask you to
notice is you're all in a room right now
when i can tell no one's driving
fortunately or no one's um
going for a walk in the park but just
notice
how aware are you of the space around
you how much
are you focusing on me versus like oh
yeah there's actually space above my
head and space behind me and
all the stuff around me as well and as
we go through
the next half hour of content and half
an hour of q
a see what happens to
both your sense of trying your effort
and how aware you are of the wider space
around you and we'll play with this and
come back to it
um at various points but just to give
you a sense of these are the kind of
things we're playing with
and it's fun to be able to observe these
things in real time while watching me
and engaging with this kind of content
so great let me talk about first of all
what is the alexander technique and my
god this is one of my least favorite
questions
because it's so difficult to actually
define what this thing is it's like
asking what is philosophy or what is zen
um and trying to answer that in a short
pithy way is difficult
but what i would say right now is it's a
way of
noticing how we are being in
our day-to-day activities
it's noticing how we habitually respond
to stimuli both internally and
externally
it's being able not to respond to them
in those habitual ways
and then allow something else to happen
instead a more constructive conscious
thing that is not habitual
and at this point i think it's useful to
talk a little bit about the story
of frederick matthias alexander and how
he developed this thing
um here he is uh you can tell from the
name of the book man supreme inheritance
that he was
not particularly modest about the
potential for his thing um
and his story was that he was a
shakespearean recital recitalist orator
from tasmania and he
really enjoyed what he did but when he
went up on stage he noticed after all
that he would lose his voice he would go
horse
when he was performing and he
he went to see a doctor who said look
rest take a break don't do too much
talking and it'll come back
it'll be fine so he did this he rested
he went back home
on stage and once again it helped a
little bit but halfway through his
big performance he lost his voice again
so
rather than um going back to the doctor
and saying let's just rest
indefinitely it's clearly not working he
noticed fortunately that
this only happened to him when he was up
on stage giving a recital
it was only when he was in public
speaking mode
if you like that he lost his voice and
what he he realized that he must be
doing something to himself
must be something different in the
context of being on stage that he wasn't
doing day-to-day environment
so he set up an elaborate system of
mirrors at home
and when he went to act out go into that
mode he saw that he was compressing
himself he was
pulling his head back and down and he
was doing various things to interfere
with the natural functioning of his his
uh vocal system
so we thought ah cool fine done i'll
just not do that
right um and try as he might to not
do that he still did it and in fact i've
made it worse
um so
by noticing that he didn't have as much
conscious control as he thought he did
um
he realized there's something else going
on right so
his mission turned more into how do you
not
interfere with yourself how do you allow
something else to kick in instead
so that's where it comes from the way
it's normally taught in
[Music]
normal conventional lessons and how i
trained as well
is that it's not too touch in person
via the body so in the same way as
alexander was like okay i'm doing
something to my body
the way into this system is is via is
via the body
um so if we were in person if you want
to see a teacher
what one of the first things that would
happen is that they would put their
hands on your on your head on your neck
and make a small adjustment in the
relationship between your skull and your
spine which incidentally
um is um just between your ears
behind your eyes it's not anywhere in
the back here but that's the thing we
would normally do as a little
party trick um to kind of ask you where
these things are
so i obviously can't do this
in this context particularly in the
context of a pandemic
i can't reach through the screen and put
my hands on you and do that kind of
thing
and i think a lot of
the alzheimer's technique profession
right now is
um wondering how to um adapt to the
current times
where the mangrove teachings in person
and now we just can't do that
um so instead my approach has been
to start from the idea that this thing
is teachable
online and then how would we do that um
well the way that i i do it and the way
that
fortunately the way that i train was
very not body focused it was very much
more in the language of zen and taoism
and a lot of these mindfulness
traditions and the body stuff
is a useful thing to play with
adjacently
it's a very good way in but it's not the
point
shall we say and there's a principle
amazon technique called psychophysical
unity
which is also known as body mind i would
say in other traditions
where there's no such thing as a purely
mental act and there's no thing as a
purely physical act
it's all one system it's all one process
so as you go to move your arm move your
hand
that's not just a physical moving of the
it's a mental component as well it's
actually one
one system so in an in-person lesson
particularly the way that i've trained
you would notice very quickly a
a subjective change in your experience
of
space and i call this expanded awareness
and i've seen this reference in books as
well
as i'd say expanded awareness um
and i've realized i think other teachers
are doing similar things as well is that
you can use this sense of expanded
awareness
as a kind of virtual training
environment a a subjective
um testing space to see what happens
um and how you can um engage with
yourself
in the world and how you respond to
these stimuli
so i asked you at the beginning to
assess how how closely how how where are
you of the space around you
particularly face above you and behind
you and while we've been
well i've been talking while you've been
listening to me has that changed
has there been some kind of change in
your experience to the space
now you can't answer me of course um so
i'll just uh give you a like ask the
question
but i would hazard a guess that um
there will be some kind of collapsing so
there's something
special about both um computer screens
and people
in that we're we're very easily
attracted by them if you like um so
when i focus too much on the on the
webcam and i'm going to collapse my
awareness this is what happens
everything just kind of goes
almost like this um and when that
happens
there's corresponding changes in my body
and this is where the psychophysical
unity stuff comes in
because if i were to switch off my
awareness
then i end up like this i kind of i do
the whole slouching thing
and moreover i if i
care too much about the screen i'll kind
of end up doing this
and this is how you kind of find
yourself like
hours later while doing you know you're
kind of like what am i doing why
why am i in here why am i in this space
and the reason for this
is well i've lost the space above me
behind me
i'm just down here so this is one reason
why this is
a useful thing now this expanded
awareness thing
it's it's hard to describe exactly why
it's a valuable thing but like i said
it's a
it's a training environment it's a thing
that you can use subjectively it's like
an n equals one
um scientific method system of
um what's going on and how you respond
into the world so if you get your
expanded awareness going on
um i posit if you like that
this is a kind of non-interference
this is when i am not getting involved
in
stuff like listening to someone talking
i'm not getting overly involved
i'm not worried about something i'm not
off somewhere
i'm here in the present moment and not
only in the present moment i'm in all of
it
in all directions all at once and this
is where the special thing comes in
because it's not just
i'm noticing sounds i'm not saying that
kind of thing it's almost like awareness
is shaped
and it is shaped above my head and
behind me and around in all directions
all at once
so something i often do and i haven't
got my phone to hand unfortunately but
let's assume that i'm reading this book
there's the guy again isn't he
good looking guy um let's say that i'm
overly involved
i can just collapse into it right now
something's going on here i've gone
somewhere
like i've checked out of the real world
in a way
and i've gone into some other space now
what is going on there if i were looking
at twitter which i want to do
and i kind of it's been 10 15 minutes
and i suddenly come back
where have i been i've been unconscious
in some way
and there's in that in that space
there's a lack of
choice there's a lack of agency because
if i'm scrolling twitter for 15 minutes
just liking things going oh isn't this
great
i'm stuck i can't do anything else until
i
come come to my senses come back to
myself and it's funny we use a language
like that
um and then um
i'm free of this thing i've been
hypnotized now and back
so by maintaining the spatial awareness
then we can give ourselves more agency
more choice
more freedom if you like and one of them
the
one of the best books on a t and that's
called freedom to choose
for that reason if you give yourself
agency and freedom to choose
so what i'd like to
show you is a couple of things you can
do with this and i'm aware that i said
half an hour of
uh talking and it's been about 15
minutes doesn't time fly when you're
having fun
um is to show you a couple of ways
that this can be played with so
first of all let's just re-expand out
again and i'll give you a couple of
exercises for this and i've seen lot
kelly appear a couple of times in the
chat
and i'm going to use one of one of his
mindfulness prompts which i think is
excellent but first of all
let's give you a sense of space and it's
kind of
a noticing it's like a remembering
there's no effort required here but
you'll notice that there is a kind of
effort that wants to kick in
so let's start with up so just check in
if there were an
aircraft going 10 000 feet overhead just
check that you could
notice it just check that you would hear
it if it were that
now i can see a couple of people doing
something that's a bit of a trap here
which is two if you look at me um can i
go like
okay it's up yeah there's it's a ba
flight it's a 747
and i've gone up there right i've i've
detached from myself down here and i've
sent myself
up there so don't do that
stay here stay in the room stay there
where we are now
and expand upwards such that you would
notice that sound if it were there
so you're still here and
you could notice the sound of that
aircraft where there so all you're doing
is opening up
that direction now let's do this in
other directions
let's do this behind behind us so
there's two ways of doing this
you can either imagine a conversation
behind you in the room
and don't lose the one above you it's
still there so there's that aircraft and
there's a conversation behind you just
check that you could notice it
or to get even closer to the the heart
of this
i would say whatever it is that you're
doing in this direction
okay just get a sense of it do it in
that direction
because it's not a word thing like it's
not the kind of
we can use tricks and you know the
finger that points to the moon is not
the moon
type stuff so listen for that aircraft
check that you could notice it
cool check figure out what the moon is
in that context
and then apply the moon backwards in
order actions
so right now just be in the middle of
this space
in all directions and this is where that
prompt from lot kelly comes in
where he says what's here now when
there's no problem to solve
and that's great because it takes us
into the present moment and into all of
it
and then when something comes up
then we just go like no thanks no we're
good when there's no problems to solve
right
um i'll come back to you later uh so
come up to that spaciousness and now
from here i'd like you to notice what
happens when i ask you to call to mind
the thorniest item on your to-do list
for monday
suffering so
what was that collapse like did you
notice it did you notice how you kind of
glitched
in a way or there was some kind of like
feeling that is a stimulus
i gave you a stimulus and you responded
in a
habitual kind of way to it right which
often comes with a
collapse it comes with a sense of
dropping and narrowing and
smallering if i wanted a better word
so without going into too much detail
now because we haven't really got the
time or the space
i would say the way around this
trap this habitual response is to
notice that notice something happened
i collapsed i have been fortunate about
the word triggered
and i can choose consciously to
re-expand myself
i can choose to expand out the aircraft
in all space around me
and allow this thing this idea of my
my thorny task my to-do list or whatever
it might be
um to be there in the space
and also there is everything else so
when i think about my so i work for a
big four audit firm
surprise um when i think about my to-do
list for monday
it's not great um my awareness naturally
kind of goes like
and there's this tightness in my body
and it just sucks so
what i can do instead is like it is
there right
but it doesn't have to dominate my
entire being it doesn't have to dominate
my entire awareness
and it's only the fact that this thing
has power over me that i can collapse
down
and if i were to collapse down and just
live inside the space
um that my to-do list exists in that
sucks
that's an unpleasant way of being now i
can do two things i can force it away
i can just say like no i don't want that
push push push distract twitter
um kind of works leads to more suffering
um or i can expand us okay there it is a
very practical thing you can do with
this skill
is in the domain of chronic pain
so let's say that i have pain in my
wrist
and chronic pain is the kind of thing
that says like something wrong
there's nothing i can do to fix it it's
chronic i can't make it go away
now pain is very powerful in that it
attracts our attention in a very
powerful very strong direct irritating
way
and all we're really aware of is the
pain our awareness collapses to the size
of the pain
and that therefore all of our experience
is pain
now again we can try and push this away
we can distract ourselves we can numb it
in some way
twitter alcohol whatever it might be
um people um and that also
it kind of it works but we're being
dominated by this thing we're still
defining ourselves in relationship to
the pain
right it's still kind of the thing
that's causing us to be on twitter
if you like so instead what we can do is
notice that our awareness has collapsed
down to the size of the pain
and zoom out right so do this noticing
of the aircraft in all directions
noticing what's here now when there's no
problem to solve
and the pain doesn't go anywhere but it
stays the same size if it's a box of
this size
and my awareness gets huge and infinite
then the proportion of my awareness
which is pain is smaller
so yes there is pain and yes i can go
and make a coffee if i want to
and yes i can go for a walk and yes i
can do something else
and the pain will want to bring you back
into it but i can say no and it's that
saying no
in a constructive way that is at the
core of alzheimer's technique it's
called inhibition
um in amazon technique and it actually
predates freud um so it's not kind of
being uninhibited and sensitive like
repressed
um it's a constructive skill of stimulus
okay no allow something else to happen
so looking at the time okay
one more thing i would like to give you
with this
sense is
what an asylum technique is called the
primary control um
which is essentially a natural thing
that all
mammals i think is how we framed it have
um which is how we are fully switched on
and alive
um if you ever seen a feline hunting
something
it's clearly engaged with its primary
control switched on it leaves from the
eyes and the head that kind of thing
um now this is where the hands-on
element
is very valuable in in-person teaching
because you can basically switch it onto
touch
and there's some witchcraft at this
point where if i switch on my primary
control and put my hand on your neck and
then i can take you into it
i can switch on yours to touch it's
magical i can't do it here but
there may be other ways and i think
there are of switching this thing on and
i'm going to give you one of the the
more simple ones that i've figured out
here
so right now keep the expansion above
you right just be aware of that space
now if i were down here and i was aware
of that space
i'm i'm aware of it but it's not going
to help me i'm not going to not
necessarily float up
lightly like i want to but
let's assume well we'd have to assume we
know that right now below us
there is a planet right you don't have
to remind
yourself or convince yourself in any way
that there's a gravitational field
down right you just know this and i say
just know in a very
kind of a direct way now what i'd like
you to do
is equivalently just know that there is
a planet overhead
and it's exerting a gravitational field
on you right now
and it's pulling you up kind of
lengthening you
and all you have to do is allow it to do
so
there's something you have to do nothing
you have to force
or no effort required there's already a
natural upward flow
that exists and all you have to do is
get out of the way
now some of you might be noticing little
shifts in your body
at this point some kind of decompression
some kind of like oh i'm a little bit
higher up than i was i'm a little bit
lighter than i was
again in in-person lessons this would be
quite a strong
experience depending on how sensitive
you were to it now in this instance
i don't know how strong it is for you um
and it might be quite mild
but what i would say is in the same way
as the finger that points at the moon
it's not the moon
what's the moon in that context what are
you doing get a sense for whatever it is
that you're doing to trigger this
slight lengthening process that was
triggered by the the idea of the
by the planet of overhead whatever that
was
turn it up just more of it
allow it even more
and sometimes this comes with a sense of
relief a sense of oh this is nice
um and then the funny thing is
and maybe we can do this in the q a it's
very easy for the mind
now to wonder what the hell is going on
right so at this point you had a couple
of moments of
oh that was lovely what was i doing to
create this
brain kicks in going like oh well i was
imagining a planet and it's up there and
um and we're stuck right so whatever it
was that you were just doing
to experience that lengthening is not
what you were gonna like try and do now
and this is a very easy trap and in fact
is the core of the trap
that alexander technique gets us out of
very similarly if you you see this in in
sports where the batsman
hits an amazing home run chokes because
like oh
this was amazing how do i do it again
well i was staying like this i i moved
my hand at this time i breathed in this
way like no no that's not what you were
doing
none of that is what you were doing when
you hit the home run you're doing none
of that
right actually you were not even caring
about the home run you just hit the home
run
but you can very easily get stuck in the
in the the cycle
of that so when that happens
my best advice is just to notice it
because any kind of trying to fix it
will amplify
the thing that it isn't if you like
so okay there's that planet it's already
overhead
allow yourself to lengthen up towards it
notice
any desire any impulse to analyze this
to figure out what's going on or to even
do it
right notice it and you can just say no
not going to engage with that i'm going
to stay in this process
so i think i've covered the half hour
roughly of my my content i was going to
say it to you and i can see 99 plus
things in the chat you will be very
active um
so i think that's a good place to pause
and we can discuss any anything that
comes up now
right so if you have any questions start
throwing in the chat but i have a cue or
question beforehand
um i think most of these are just the
random statements
so i'll ask one uh to warm michael up
and then
we'll go to the chats uh i'm curious how
long have you been doing this and what
kind of like benefits you've seen
personally in all the different areas
and domains of life from doing it
sure so i started training in 2014
i did a part-time for three years um
which is unconventional normally you do
uh full-time training um i think 1600
hours is the target so i did evenings
and weekends for three years
i'm graduating 2017 and since then my
main uh engagement
with this content is in
training other trainees to become
teachers so i help out at the school i
train that basically
um otherwise i have a job and i've been
doing the stuff online on twitter and
kind of doing whatever i can to stay
involved
um in terms of benefits i think the
the biggest ones are a sense of
confidence and ease
i think i've changed quite a lot as a
person having done this
so for example in the half hour before
this
session i noticed hey there's a bunch of
anxiety here
um this is a stressful thing to be in
your home and then push a button and
have
53 people looking at you while you talk
about a heart described thing
and that's fine like this this anxiety
was allowed to be there
and then so is everything else right i
didn't push it away
i didn't engage with it it's like oh
look there's anxiety and there's the
world let me carry on
so that kind of thing of just a sense of
trust in myself
and moreover of course the kind of i now
have much better posture and
i you know all that stuff as well but in
terms of like the fundamental change in
who i am i think is really the biggest
thing
awesome all right so we're going to
pivot to the chats and i imagine we're
going to have a bunch of questions
coming up so we're not going to get to
all of them and i'm not going to ask
them in the order that they
come in so
yeah let's malcolm had one above and you
just rewrote it so malcolm ocean
if you're gonna meet yourself and ask
michael your question yeah can you hear
me
yes cool um so
yeah so my my question is um you're
saying you know if we're
if we're aware then we kind of stand in
this kind of gravitationally balanced
way if we're unaware that we slouch
and um i guess my question is why if
unaware
do we slouch as opposed to for instance
some other
either some other sort of broken path
like you know some somehow unbalanced
posture
or like you know if i if i'm unaware of
my
my phone it doesn't like fall off my
desk like what yeah
what systems are causing it to do
something
else and can those be retrained so that
we would actually have a relaxed posture
even if
unaware anyway there's a whole cluster
of questions here
sure the first one that comes to mind is
essentially exploring what you mean by
good posture
and kind of what what balance even is
so when let's say you go to the pub
or let's say i get club it's very
frequent thing for me um
and you you kind of you're involved in
the conversation had a few drinks and
you want to kind of
shut down and just be balanced right you
what you do is you lock your leak knees
back
you push your pelvis forwards and you
assume a kind of a very locked
position you might even lean against the
bar now at that point you have
achieved balance right you're not going
to fall over
but you're not exactly alive right
you're kind of detached
so the kind of good posture balance and
upright
this thing i was pointing at is very
much dynamic
so call it a kind of a dynamic balance
that's always
adjusting itself it's always reorienting
itself
such that if i was standing somewhere my
knees are unlocked my pelvis is kind of
aligned with my body
and at any moment i could go anywhere
right i wouldn't have to first
unlock and then take a few steps i could
just take some steps
in any direction any time
so the system that we're talking about
is one that requires consciousness
the fact that you have good posture in
the way that i'm talking about implies
that you have good consciousness you are
there
at the time if you check out if you turn
off your consciousness your body will
assume a position
that means that you haven't got to look
after it it's just kind of on hold
if you like that's how i fail anyway
right cool that makes a lot of sense
it's sort of like asking you know
in samuel burgess thing it's like you
know well why don't dead players just
act like live players
instead of like well they they have to
operate in ways that work
without that level of consciousness yes
and like
yeah cool
cool thanks malcolm uh evan you had a
question
are you going to mute yourself hi thanks
so
um very much enjoyed everything so far
my question relates to multitasking this
question occurred to me seeing the
frenetic activity in the chat and i i've
done a lot of work with various mind
body things vagina martial arts
yoga some alexander technique and the
more i've done that stuff the more i
develop what i feel like is an allergy
to multitasking because it seems like
multitasking comes
inherently with some level of
contraction as you described it earlier
so i was wondering what your thoughts
were on the relationship between
multitasking and contraction
is it possible to multitask in a fully
present and alive and aware sense with
no compromises you know just kind of rip
on that
great i love it um i subscribe to the
belief that there's no such thing as
multitasking honestly
it's very rapid mono focus
and in fact this is a good segue into
what is attention versus what is
awareness um so for me attention moves
around with an awareness and this is
well established in some practices but
otherwise it's mind-blowing
so if your if your awareness is
collapsed
into a single task and you then have to
expand
out shift across that's a huge load
if your awareness is just broad and open
and you are lightly moving your
attention from a to b
with consciously that's okay as long as
you're aware the fact that you're
changing your mono focus right um it's
when you're unconscious
that it's like it's just a dragging
across of both attention and awareness
you're just not aware of the awareness
part of it
often
awesome all right julie you had a
question
sir is that me yes did i pronounce your
name yeah
uh lulu yes um hi uh so i was curiou
when you were talking about the primary
control and and
how um touch can allow it to uh
like magically work um are there
particular parts of the body where that
are sort of more magical than others
and and like kind of how does that work
like i'm kind of thinking about
um like to what extent can this be
done at home during lockdown in covid
times and like is that and
i want to kind of understand a bit more
about that
yes there's a lot in that um so if i
were if i were teaching in person
the way that i would help people to
switch that thing on is to notice where
they are
holding in some way where they are
habitually
locking part of their body and it's very
commonly something like putting pelvis
forwards
or um compressing their their neck that
that kind of thing um and then inviting
that to not happen
um hold them and keep them in that kind
of new space the unknown
um dynamic equilibrium that i was
talking about and then
that enables this thing now in person
like also when you're on your own
obviously you have access to a teacher
so
what i play with is so first of all turn
on as much as you can what i've talked
for you so far so
have the spatial awareness open as far
as possible be
aware of the idea of this thing going
upwards and then
use intention when you do things when
you move and walk in particular
so let's say that i'm walking across the
street there are different ways that you
can do that you can
lead with your chest you can lead with
your hips you can leave with your knees
and a ministry of city walk style um
what i would
invite is to lead with your intention
so i want to be over there and i'm
allowing myself to go over there
and then let your body follow almost
kind of like how you see a child
like they don't organize their body when
they walk they decide i want to be over
there
and then i'll let myself get closer to
it i don't know i don't care how
kind of thing um that's the closest i
can come to right now
um to tell you how to activate this this
is the hardest thing that i found
to teach online um i can teach the
innovation stuff much more easily but
this i'm still working on this is my
edge currently if you like
because alexander did create it without
having someone to have taught him um
did he did he have a mirror or something
so he had mirrors so he had a mirror in
front of him later on he had a system
where he could see himself sideways but
what he did is called directions in
amazon technique so
i honestly i don't entirely believe the
story he came up with
um necessarily um
but his story is that he basically sat
there
for a very long time not doing anything
so he would inhibit every and he would
so he would not respond to
every stimulus that was conditioned in
some way
right and then he would say okay well
let kind of he'd use words
he describes like allow the the neck to
be free
to let the head go forward and up and
the backs lengths and wide and all this
kind of thing
and he he said to use these words direct
these words
um and it would happen now for me it's
kind of the same as the finger and the
moon
and the fine he was saying these words
and something would happen but it wasn't
the words that were doing it they were
just a way in for him
um so i'm reluctant and i don't teach
this way i don't teach directions
in that way because i think it can
easily get in the way
so i would just say whatever it is when
you've noticed something that seems like
what i'm describing
notice what that thing is and then just
do it again
play with them or turn up right
very cool all right uh margaret you had
a question above
if you're gonna meet yourself
thank you michael this is uh very useful
uh my question which started to be
answered in the chat
um but is how does the alexander
technique hold space
for the seeming influx of information
that can arise when one begins to access
this sense of spaciousness and continued
mindfulness
i know at least the personal experience
when
whether you call it holding patterns or
seed other another nomenclature but um
when you unlock those there's like a
huge energetic release within the body
which can be
extremely overwhelming and um re-trigger
trauma responses and
i'm just curious if there's kind of like
safety or controls built into the
alexander technique to allow people to
titrate their experience at a pace of
their own choosing
so i've seen this kind of thing come up
in in-person lessons where someone
when you release physical holding
particularly
that releases some kind of trauma
response and something comes up i've
definitely seen that and the holding of
space i've seen
is
it's a it's being there with the person
in a teaching context
is being there with them it's
it's helping them
to not get involved in what's coming up
in the same ways i've been showing
inhibition which is the collapse of
awareness into the thing
um that's how i experience it and then
zooming out again
you can notice oh hey there's this
trauma response coming up
i could very easily get involved in it
tell my story stories go and do things
try and accelerate it whatever
you can inhibit that response as well
and it's kind of inhibition all the way
down
if you like um so something comes up
inhibit the response let it do its thing
um
if i think for safety reasons if you
think there's some kind of
reason why you'd have strong trauma
responses go and do it to the teacher
um because they would have more capacity
to help you in that moment but that's
true of
many practices where you should be
careful just in general
um and there are lists of teachers um in
professional bodies
um websites that you can look up and i
highly recommend that um
one thing i found titration in fact when
i come across
something that is too much um i can zoom
in and out if you like
um so if i want to make an experience
more intense
i can actually compress my awareness a
bit so it takes up more like okay i want
to go into some more
very consciously it's it's a bit cheeky
almost
but i can make it more intense and it
was just too much okay whoa whoa
okay birds birds trees um other stuff
and it's just it becomes a bit smaller
right so i think that's that's the the
most coaching like me right now but if
you're worried then
go and go and see a teacher i would say
thank you
yeah i guess um
the reason i ask the question is because
i know like in the yoga space for
example
similar experiences can come up for
people and
at least in many yoga traditions they
start with teaching the breath
as your anchor for awareness so that
whatever else happens you can come back
to this point
and of the breath and as i'm sure anyone
who's experienced like an anxiety or
panic attack knows like the breath can
be
something that sends you out into it and
it can also take you back
and so what i'm hearing is that this
skill itself which may
trigger these states is also the tool
that one should focus on in order to
find find a flow within
those experiences yes exactly and one
thing i would add is that
as a teacher i have to be very careful
in person
not to take someone too far if you like
um so if i if there's like it's very
intuitive
like when i figure okay why put my hands
next there's no rationale behind it
necessarily it's kind of like i'm drawn
to a particular area
and if there's a huge resistance i might
subtly invite change
um but i'm not going to force it because
their system isn't ready for it yet
so what i would suspect is if you're
doing it on your own at home
i would doubt that you would get to a
place where you would
unlock a massive trauma response because
you're just not available for it
and it would happen incrementally and
slowly but there is definitely
a responsibility on my part in person to
not force something on you that you're
not able to have
if you're like thank you my last thought
and then i'll stop talking so other
people can is just that um
it sounds almost like what you're
describing is nervous system attunement
right and that you are
grounding in your own nervous system and
then by holding space for your students
they can also access that within their
bodies
yes exactly and there's a whole bunch of
stuff that i can't really go into in
this context
like i could just take too long about
how
the teacher putting hands on a student
is
essentially i'd be mapping your system
in my system right so we are one
system and what i notice in myself is
going on in you and that kind of thing
so i can modify my own experience
to modify yours and this is where it
gets a little bit woo
um but i've tested it it does work and
there's a reason for it i don't know why
i don't ask me how it works i listen
that does work
but yes i agree with that
all right thank you maybe gray you had a
question
hey michael i'm so excited to see you
here i've been looking forward to this
session ever since it got announced so
thank you so much for being here
um my question is about um alexander
technique and mental pension
when you initially asked us to check in
um
about our effort levels i noticed that a
lot of mine was that kind of fierce
energetic monkey mind like oh i'm ready
to focus on some alexander technique
learning
um and i did notice that when i imagined
you know the gravity
that comes from above it it seemed like
it pulled out a bunch of that
monkey mind shatter in addition to you
know lower back tension
and things like that so i just wonder if
alexander technique knows that it's
doing that and if it like
tries to attack that kind of
mental attention and inhibit that as
well
i would say it absolutely does know it's
sitting with that stuff um
it's this is the principle of
psychophysical unity so if i if i have
tension in my body that does correspond
it's not body tension it's not mental
tension
it's a pattern of holding right
so yes i can release i can help you to
release or to not be doing the thing
that's causing the attention in your
body
equally i can help you to not be doing
the thing causing the holding in your
mind
because it's one process and we can kind
of interact back and forth between body
and mind in that way
so that's why i was talking about the
biggest effects i've seen in my own life
are
they are partly physical i mean i'm i'm
much more
following that word loose and upright
but it's really the mental health
benefits and the kind of the ease and
lightness
and just finding uh a sense of
fluidity in things and i can now catch
myself getting stuck in like oh look i'm
doing this thing
with the do this or i'm getting involved
with this person or whatever
let me not do that right let me have
this skill set that i can use to not be
getting involved in these things before
we're unconscious
and that's very much a mental process as
well yeah
i i just immediately get this um feeling
of
i can see how it's so hard for you to
explain
because it's like you're so
interconnected and you're doing
something
that's changing all of your responses
across all of your systems and i can see
how it would be really difficult
to communicate how special that is like
all the way across the board so thank
you so much for
putting in the effort today thank you
and i will just add that there's
there is the difficulty in the fact that
most conventional teaching is done in
the frame of posture improvement or
you've got lower back pain come and see
an ot teacher or
like no no no no no it really just
doesn't help
the rest of us trying to get beyond that
frame
cool thank you maybe uh ikem
you had a question above if you'd like
to unmute yourself
yes thank you how are you michael thank
you
i assume there is no such thing as being
fully aware at least consciously
24 7. and i'm amazed by the fact that
we're
driven 95 by our subconscious mind so
i'm
wondering if there is any way maybe
through repetition to transfer this task
to our
subconscious mind so be as aware as
possible
uh as long as possible
absolutely um so when i first began
training
the the game if you like was noticing
that sense of expansion that i've
shown you today and then the the
assignment if like was okay
between now and next session your only
job is to notice it
right remember this thing exists um at
the very beginning
that's the entire practice right you're
not we're not good at this to begin with
we are habituated
to not do this now where i am now after
three years of teacher training and a
few years of just living it
is that it's almost like there's a part
of my my mind my being
that is constantly pinging the world um
it's like
is it there is it there is it there and
i'll give this one away that
my own teacher says the present moment
only lasts for three seconds
so you can't be mindful once and then
say i'm mindful
i'm gonna hang on to this now all day
all right it's like no
there's the world there's the space
there it is
there it is there it is and you keep
asserting it you keep choosing it
and the what you're talking about there
is that the
the the habit of choosing it
becomes more ingrained with time
all right so now i don't need to be
thinking through that the planet or the
space or whatever it's just like
that and it's always there it goes up
and down
but i very much live what i speak and in
fact you can't teach this
unless you are embodying what i'm
talking about if you just put your hands
on someone
it nothing will happen unless you switch
this thing on for yourself so all i
would recommend is
for now pay attention to that this thing
exists
and keep practicing it as you're going
for a walk as you're talking to someone
as you're engaged in work whatever it
might be
like how where are you the face behind
you just check in and keep checking in
and it will become easier and easier
all right mark you had a question i
believe
yeah i was i was thinking about how to
walk to the other side of the street
by just setting the intention and not
making effort
and i tried to grasp it and i was
wondering
something similar happened when you have
these prompts so you said
notice the space backwards and even
before me doing anything
something was changing me because my
attention got redirected
is it so i just want to ask you to
is it this is this the move is this the
thing
that that you think of something and
then by magic somehow it
it activates the body like the prompts
how they activate
did it mean or is it something different
or
it's so
the spatial awareness thing that i'm i
originally walked through
is sort of similar to inhibition so it's
not responding it's just being
present and non-reactive the moving in
the world
is based on intention so i want to be
over there
and the way that the clearest way that i
found this working is
to set a clear intention and then let go
of the need to achieve it
almost um so for example when i was
training
um i would spend less than upon lesson
playing catch
with my with my teacher and if any all
of you have played catchphrase at some
point and you know the ritual response
is like oh my god
gotta catch the ball um because we're
just
it looks bad to drop it that kind of
thing it is possible to not care
about catching the ball completely while
still intending
to catch the ball and that's when your
hand just goes there elegantly naturally
and you kind of you hit the ball
perfectly feel that and that kind of
thing
now there's something coming up that i
want to share
about what intention actually is and
this is a little exercise so we have a
couple of minutes hopefully
so if you could all just like put your
hand up like this but you're put your
face up by the slingsie okay
i want to just like to say using your
commanding internal like doing voice
open close open close
right so you can see these two things
are coincident you can open and close
your hand while yelling at yourself
to open close now i'd like you to keep
your hands shut
while going open close open close
yell at you if you want at your hand
oh look nothing's happening right you're
doing something else that isn't the
word in your head to open and close now
just to really make this point
really clear i want you to
yell if you like command your hand to
close close
close and then just do this
how did you do that
whatever that thing is that's how you
set an intention to cross the road
yeah i love that exercise
all right uh maybe we have time for one
or two more questions
um brian you had a question on being
drunk i'm hi michael just now is you
mentioned about
um drink going to the pub and i was
actually very curious because i think
um when i'm when i'm drinking i and i've
like did drunk like drink too much and
just did that strong and i do have
i do use deep breathing and i manage my
posture
um and expanding my awareness with
with the world do you have a similar
experience
and possibly um
possibly your um use case of like
uh experiencing using the alexander
technique uh
alongside um stuff like alcohol
or like uh i mean i smoke a lot and
right now i feel the urge
to smoke i feel the problem and i am
consciously telling myself i'm trying to
quit
so i'm consciously telling myself away
aware of this
urge and no stop no there is there is
this is just
prompt but i am aware and i am not
setting the intention to move so
possibly
it has there been like any uh funny
experiences like
when you go to the pub and stuff
the one of the one of the annoying
things about learning
amazon technique is that once you
realize that you have choice
you can't get out of that like you're
just oh i'm drinking because i'm
choosing to drink okay fine
um you know no longer off the hook um
for being unconscious
so what i'm what i what comes up for me
for that question is
let's say you want to drink less or stop
smoking or something
pay close attention to what the urge is
like
the idea will come up oh hey i could
have a cigarette right now i could smoke
right now
what does that do to your awareness
right does it go does it collapse around
the thought
does your does your entire existence
become the idea that you have a
cigarette
if that's the case it's really a lot of
work to fight back to resist that
so another way is to zoom out in the way
that i've been talking about
allow that urge to be there
without pushing it away without saying
you are bad for wanting this you are you
should know bad no
you should not do this like an annoyed
parent
um neither go like oh look a squirrel
let's allow it to be there and choose
like no
my intention is i'm not going to do this
right so neither engaging nor pushing
away
in the context of giving yourself choice
to do something else
right and when you have this space you
have choice not to engage in activity
cool all right so let's close out
here um michael any any kind of uh
final words for us or any place we can
find you to learn more about what you're
doing
sure so i guess my my final words are
just play with this i've we've gone
through a couple of things
and hold this lightly
as you go for walks as you engage and
stuff just notice that this stuff
is always there and you always have this
spaciousness accessible to you
it's just that if you choose to access
it in terms of where to find me
um the best place for this kind of
content is my my newsletter expanding
awareness
um which is
expandingawareness.substance.com
um i write periodically there but as i'm
technique and i'm also building
um a course i'm trying to figure out how
to teach this
properly online and that's the main port
of call for that if you are someone who
has
bought the course and i recognize a few
of you here um you will see some of this
content
appear over there um please forgive me
it'll grow
so i'm looking forward to seeing you in
there as well if you're one of them
beautiful and i will put michael's um
website in the chats
uh michael thank you so much for coming
to the store today that was the lovely
session and uh
i learned a lot and i imagine everyone
else in the room learned a lot as well
so thank you so much for
for coming thank you it's been a real
pleasure
so i'll make some upcoming announcements
on events uh you can check out the
we got so many freaking events coming up
uh on sunday we have
one uh 6 p.m eastern time called raw
femininity
and we're having these raw series maybe
gray led the way with her raw sexuality
but we have like raw masculinity like
raw mortality
and it's just that with the stova
village we're having conversations
around a certain theme and they've been
quite fun
uh you can rsvp um there
on the website and then on monday we
have something
event called pandemic of groupthink jung
and the collective
shadow with this irish character uh uber
boyo uh he's coming in that's 12 p.m
uh eastern time you can all speak there
the website the snow.ca
for more events and if you'd like to
support us
on uh at the stoa you can do so on
patreon while we
steal the culture seduce the culture
heal the culture all that jazz
that being said thank you again michael
and everyone for joining the store today